Guide to the Ernest Nagel Papers, 1925-1982 ASP.2020.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ernest Nagel Papers
1925-1985
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Nagel, Ernest
ASP.2020.01
8.75 Linear Feet (7 record center boxes)
The collection contains personal and professional correspondence written and received by Ernest Nagel, an American Philosopher of Science, who along with contemporaries Hans Reichenbach, Rudolf Carnap and Carl Hempel is one of the major figures of the logical positivist movement. His work concerned the philosophy of mathematical fields such as geometry and probability, quantum mechanics, and the status of reductive and inductive theories of science, and his book The Structure of Science is recognized as an inaugural work in the field of analytic philosophy of science.
Acqusition Information
Gift of Alexander Joseph Nagel and Sidney Robert Nagel in 2020.
Scope and Content Notes
The Ernest Nagel Papers are comprised of correspondence received by Nagel between 1925-1985. Individual correspondence to Nagel from other scholars includes Rudolph Carnap, Carl Gustav Hempel, Sidney Hook, Susan Stebbing and Alfred Tarski. Correspondence with organizations includes many of the professional organizations in which Nagel participated and served in an administrative capacity, including his time as editor of the Journal of Philosophy (1939–1956) and the Journal of Symbolic Logic (1940-1946). Topical Files include documentation of offprints, reviews, and comments on scholarly articles by Nagel as well as information and newsclippings that document his participation in the national teach-in on the Vietnam War in 1965.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The Ernest Nagel Papers are arranged in three series:
Series I. Correspondence with Individuals, 1925-1985
Series II. Correspondence with Organizations, 1928-1949
Series III. Topical Files, 1925-1980
Biography
Ernest Nagel was an American philosopher of science who is regarded as one of the major figures of the logical positivist movement. Nagel was born in Nové Mesto nad Váhom (now in Slovakia, then Vágújhely and part of the Austro-Hungarian Empire) in 1901. His mother, Frida Weiss, was from the nearby town of Vrbové (or Verbo). He emigrated to the United States at the age of 10 with his family and became a U.S. citizen in 1919. He earned his PhD from Columbia University in 1931 and went on to spend his academic career there, becoming the first John Dewey Professor of Philosophy at the University in 1955. His doctoral students included Morton White, Patrick Suppes, Henry Kyburg, Isaac Levi, and Sidney Morgenbesser.
Nagel made many noteworthy contributions in the fields of geometry and probability, quantum mechanics, and the status of reductive and inductive theories of science. His book The Structure of Science (1961) is viewed as an inaugural work in the field of analytic philosophy of science. Other works by Nagel include An Introduction to Logic and the Scientific Method with Morris Raphael Cohen, his CCNY teacher in 1934. In 1958, he published with James R. Newman Gödel's proof, which provided explanation for Gödel's incompleteness theorems to those not well trained in mathematical logic. He also served as editor of the Journal of Philosophy (1939–1956) and the Journal of Symbolic Logic (1940-1946).
Ernest Nagel died in New York in 1985. He had a wife, Edith Haggstrom, and two sons, Alexander Nagel (professor of mathematics at the University of Wisconsin) and Sidney Nagel (professor of physics at the University of Chicago).
Science -- Philosophy -- History -- Sources; Science -- Philosophy -- History -- 20th century; Science -- Philosophy -- History -- 20th century; Vienna circle; Logical positivism -- History -- 20th century; Nagel, Ernest; Stebbing, L. Susan (Lizzie Susan); Hook, Sidney; Hempel, Carl G. (Carl Gustav); Carnap, Rudolf, 1891-1970
- Correspondence with Individuals, 1925-1985; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I. Correspondence with Individuals includes correspondence between Ernest Nagel and other scholars and peers including Rudolph Carnap, Carl Gustav Hempel, Sidney Hook, Susan Stebbing and Alfred Tarski.
  - Abbot, E. Stanley, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aiken, Henry, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aldrich, V.C., 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alter, George, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ambrose, Alice, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barret, William, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barzun, Jacques, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bentley, Arthur, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Berenda, Carlton W., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bergman, Gustav (friend of Neurath), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bierstedt, Robert (Navy), 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Billikopf, Jacob, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Biser, Irwin, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Black, Max, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blanshard, Brand, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bliemeister, W., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Boardman, William, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Boas, George, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bocehnski, I.M., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bornstein, J., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bowdery, Barbara, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bowdery, George J., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bowers, David F., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bridgman, P.W., 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Broadman, Samuel, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bronstein, Daniel J., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Buchanan, Scott, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Buchler, Justus, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Butler, Nicholas M., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Carman, Harry J., 1943-1948 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Carnap, Rudolf, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Castell, Alburney, no date (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Church, Alonzo, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Churchman, C.West, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Clark, John Maurice, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Cobb, Raymond, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cohen, Felix S., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cohen, Gene M., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Cohen, I. Bernard, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Cohen, Morris, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Cohen, Morris, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Coss, John J., 1926-1935 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Coss, John J., 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Couch, W.T., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Cunningham, G. Watts, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Curry, Haskell B., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Curry, Haskell B., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - DeKonick, Charles, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Deming, W. Edwards, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Dennes, William R., 1938-1945 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Dewey John, 1934-1945 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Dickey-Rowam, Ethlyn, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Dingle, Herbert, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dodd, Stuart, no date (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ducasse, Curt J., 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ducasse, Curt J., 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Eckstein, Walther, 1935-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Edel, Abe, 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Edman, Irwin, 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Edman, Irwin, 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Edwards, Paul, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Enriques, Federigo, no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Farber, Marvin, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Farrell, Jim, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Feigl, Herbert, 1938-1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Finkel William, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Finkel William, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Finkel, Irene, 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fitz, Charles, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Flanders, J., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fraenkel, Al, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Frank, Phillip, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Frankel, Charles, 1942-1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Frechet, Maurice, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Freedgood, Seymour, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Freedman, Ben, no date (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Friess, Horace L., 1934-1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Fritz, Charles A., 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Frost, Corinne, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Gailan, Edwin, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Gavrin, Joseph, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Gavrin, Mrs. D., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Gonseth, F., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Goodman, Nelson, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Greenwood, Thomas, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gross, Mason W., 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Gross, Mason W., 1942-1948 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Gruen, William (edits to Logic book), 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Gutman, James, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Guttman, Jeanette M., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, August, 1934-September, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, October, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, November, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, December, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Haggstrom, Edith, 1935-1943 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Hamblen, Stewart, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Hawthorne, Charles, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hayek, F.A., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Hecht, Celia, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hecht, Selig, 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Helmer, Eileen, 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Helmer, Olaf, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hempel, Carl Gustav, 1950-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hickson, J.W.A., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hirano, J., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hocking, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hofstadter, Albert, 1934-1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, June,1934-August, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, September, 1934-October, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, November, 1934-December, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, January, 1935-May, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, June, 1935-December, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Hook, Sidney and Ann, no date (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Horkheimer, Max, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hosiasson, Janina, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Hughes, Percy, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Hull, Clark L., 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ihwestkowa, Alina, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Irving, J.A., 1938 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Jaeger, Gertrude, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Jarrell, Randall, no date (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Jefferson, H.B., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Jeffries, Harold, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Kaempffert, Waldemar (NY Times), 1938 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Kahn, Ruth and Irving, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Kallen, Horace M., 1935-1944 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Kauffmann, Felix, 1935-1941 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Kauffmann, Felix, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Kauffmann, Herbert L., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Kemble, Edwin C., 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Kennedy, Gail, 1936-1945 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Keyser, C.J., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Klapper, Paul, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Konvitz, M.R., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Korzybski, Alfred, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Kraus, David, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Krenek, Ernst, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Krikorian, Y.H., 1939-1944 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Kronker, Stanley, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Ladd, John, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Ladin, David, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Lameere, Jean, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Lange, Oscar, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Langford, C.H., 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Lazar, N., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lee, Otis, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lesser, A., 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Levi, Albert William, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lewis, C.I., 1933-1948 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lindenbaum, Janina (From Warsaw- Conditions for Jews), 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lipkin, Mack (Frida's health), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lundberg, George, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - MacIver, R.M., 1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - MacLane, Saunders, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Macleod, D.J., 1936 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Maertens, Jacqueline, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Malisoff, W.M., 1940 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Marcus, Ralph, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Marcus, Ralph, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Margenau, Henry, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Masiloff, W.M., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Matz, Joshua, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Mayer, Clara W., 1947 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - McCurdy, Jarvis, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - McGilvary, E.B., 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - McKinsey, John C., 1939-1944 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Meiner, Felix, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miller, Dickinson S., 1947 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Moch, Royce, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Moody, Ernest, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Moore, Dorothy, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Moore, G.E., 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Morris, Charles W., 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Morris, Charles W., 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Morton, W.A., 1936 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Munitz, Milton, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Murphy, Arthur, 1934-1944 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Murphy, G.E., 1940 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Naess, Erling, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Napolin, David, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Nelson, Everett J., 1936-1945 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Ness, Arne, 1937-1946 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Neurath, Otto, 1942-1944 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Newman, James R., 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Odegard, Peter, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Overstreet, H.A., 1926-1943 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Ozame, Henry, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Page, Leigh, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Pap, Arthur, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Patterson, Edwin W., 1935 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Peatmans (xmas card), 1938 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Perl, Ruth (Mrs. Irving Kahn), 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Pratt, Carroll C., 1936 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Quine, Willard V., 1938-1948 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Radiograms to Nagel, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Rainey, Bob, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Randall, John Herman Jr., 1942-1959 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Randall, Mercedes, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Ratner, Joseph, 1924-1931 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Ratner, Joseph, 1924-1931 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Ratner, Sidney, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Reach, K., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Reichenbach, Hans, 1934-1944 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Reid, Mary, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Reidenmeister, Marie (Marie Neurath), 1937 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Rice, Phillip B., 1939 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Rittner, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Rosen, Eddie, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Rosenberg, Percy, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Rosenfeld, Lenora C., 1943 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Rosenthal, Jerome, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Samtayaria (no first name), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Saposulkow, J., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Savery, William, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Schneider, Herbert, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Schultz, Henry, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Schwartz, Benjamin, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Shapiro, Meyer, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Shapiro, Meyer, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Shapiro, Meyer, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sharpe, Samuel, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sheldon, W.H., 1932-1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Slochower, Harry, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Smullyan, Arthur, 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Stebbing, Susan, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Stone, Marshall H., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Strong, C.A., 1935 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Strong, E.W., 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Swenson, David F., 1934 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Tarski, Alfred (Letters in Support of Visa), 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Tarski, Alfred, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Vetter, John J., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Vivas, Eliseo, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Walker, George W., 1940 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Weiss, Frida (Mother), 1934 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Weiss, Frida (Mother), 1935-1939 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - White, Morty G., 1943-1946 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, no date (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth and Jean Hanson, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Whitmarsh, Elizabeth, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Wiener, Phillip, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Williams, Donald C., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Wilson, B., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Winternitz, Emanuel, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Wisdom, John, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Wohlstetter, Roberta, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Wolff, Robert, 1928-1945 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Woodbridge, Frederick J.E., 1931-1938 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - World War II Soldiers, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Wright, David M., 1948 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Wundheiler, Alexander, 1940-1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Wundt, Boris M., 1940-1945 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Zilsel, Edgar, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, no date (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Correspondence with Organizations, 1928-1949; II.
  Series II. Correspondence with Organizations includes many of the professional organizations in which Nagel participated and served in an administrative capacity, including his time as editor of the Journal of Philosophy (1939–1956) and the Journal of Symbolic Logic (1940-1946).
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - American Consulate General, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - American Library Association, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - American Philosophical Association, 1935-1942 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - American Scholar, 1935-1943 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - American Statistical Association, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Associated Hospital Service of NY (re: Edith Nagel), 1943 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Association for Symbolic Logic, 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - B.H. Blackwell Ltd., 1937 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Charles S. Peirce Society, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Clarke Insurance Agency, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Columbia University Administration, 1936-1943 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Columbia University Graduate Economics Club, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Columbia University Philosophy Department, 1935-1964 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Conference on Methods in Philosophy and the Sciences (New School), 1941 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Conference on the Scientific Spirit and Democratic Faith, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Cooper Union Department Of Social Philosophy, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Fifth International Congress for the Unity of Science, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Galois Institute of Mathematics (Long Island University), 1938 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Halifax Electric Cooperative, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Harcourt Brace Company, 1933-1939 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Harcourt Brace Company, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Harvard University Tercentenary Conference, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Horace Mann Lincoln School, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Institute for Advanced Study (Princeton, N.J.), 1936 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - International Business Machines Corporation (IBM), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - ISIS Journal (Bernard), 1939-1948 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - J. Bornstein Insurance Agency, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1934-1941 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - John Wiley and Sons Publishers, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Journal of Philosophy, 1928-1943 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Lee Furman Inc. Publisher, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Library of Living Philosophers, 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - New Leader Newspaper, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - New Republic, 1934-1937 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Osiris, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Oxford University Press, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 60)